<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tree diversity on Gustavo B Paterno</title>
    <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/categories/tree-diversity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tree diversity on Gustavo B Paterno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gustavopaterno.com/categories/tree-diversity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Diverse and larger tree islands promote native tree diversity in oil palm landscapes</title>
      <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-paterno/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-paterno/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     In monoculture-dominated landscapes, recovering biodiversity is a priority, but effective restoration strategies have yet to be identified. In this study, we experimentally tested passive and active restoration strategies to recover taxonomic, phylogenetic, and functional diversity of woody plants within 52 tree islands established in an oil palm landscape. Large tree islands and higher initial planted diversity catalyzed diversity recovery, particularly functional diversity at the landscape level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining planting trees and natural regeneration promotes long-term structural complexity in oil palm landscapes</title>
      <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-kikuchi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-kikuchi/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Vegetation structural complexity has been identified as a vital factor for forest ecosystem function, stability, and resilience. However, agricultural land with much reduced structural complexity has largely replaced natural forests in the tropics. Therefore, restoring structural complexity in large-scale plantation monocultures by introducing agroforestry systems may counteract the loss of biodiversity and ecosystem functions. However, we still have limited knowledge of how the structural complexity of agroforests develops under different restoration treatments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tree diversity reduces variability in sapling survival under drought</title>
      <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-blondeel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-blondeel/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Enhancing tree diversity may be important to fostering resilience to drought-related climate extremes. So far, little attention has been given to whether tree diversity can increase the survival of trees and reduce its variability in young forest plantations. We conducted an analysis of seedling and sapling survival from 34 globally distributed tree diversity experiments (363,167 trees, 168 species, 3744 plots, 7 biomes) to answer two questions: (1) Do drought and tree diversity alter the mean and variability in plot-level tree survival, with higher and less variable survival as diversity increases?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
