<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phylogenetic diversity on Gustavo B Paterno</title>
    <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/categories/phylogenetic-diversity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Phylogenetic diversity on Gustavo B Paterno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gustavopaterno.com/categories/phylogenetic-diversity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Key concepts and a world-wide look at plant recruitment networks</title>
      <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-alcantara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-alcantara/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Plant–plant interactions are major determinants of the dynamics of terrestrial ecosystems. There is a long tradition in the study of these interactions, their mechanisms and their consequences using experimental, observational and theoretical approaches. Empirical studies overwhelmingly focus at the level of species pairs or small sets of species. Although empirical data on these interactions at the community level are scarce, such studies have gained pace in the last decade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Phylogenetic Architecture of Recruitment Networks</title>
      <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2025-gleiser/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2025-gleiser/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     Plant recruitment involves both stochastic and deterministic processes. Recruits may establish independently or interact nonrandomly with canopy plants. We explore this deterministic aspect by testing whether recruitment patterns are influenced by the phylogenetic history of canopy and recruiting plants. Since the effect of canopy plants in recruitment can be positive (facilitation), negative (competition) or neutral, we also estimated the phylogenetic signal separately for each interaction type.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diverse and larger tree islands promote native tree diversity in oil palm landscapes</title>
      <link>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-paterno/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gustavopaterno.com/publication/2024-paterno/</guid>
      <description>Abstract     In monoculture-dominated landscapes, recovering biodiversity is a priority, but effective restoration strategies have yet to be identified. In this study, we experimentally tested passive and active restoration strategies to recover taxonomic, phylogenetic, and functional diversity of woody plants within 52 tree islands established in an oil palm landscape. Large tree islands and higher initial planted diversity catalyzed diversity recovery, particularly functional diversity at the landscape level.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
